Guide to the Helen Moore Barthelme Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Helen Moore Barthelme Papers
1949-2002
2008-021
Barthelme, Helen Moore, 1927-
4.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains photographs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, short stories, and articles related to or written by Donald Barthelme and his brothers, Rick, Steve, and Peter Barthelme, as well as notes by Helen Barthelme.
Biographical Information:
Helen Barthelme was born December 18, 1927. She graduated as an honors student from Corpus Christi High School at the age of 15. After her parents separated, she moved to Houston with her mother and two sisters. About a year later, around the age of 17, she enrolled at the University of Houston, where she would later meet Donald Barthelme Jr., who would later become a famous author. She became editor of the school newspaper 'The Cougar.' After graduating with her bachelor's degree, she continued to work in the university's public relations department. She briefly left the university to start a corporate career, but returned as director of the Information Office in 1951.
In 1951, she married her first husband Pete Gilpin. The marriage dissolved in 1956, and she married Donald Barthelme shortly thereafter. She left her professional endeavors for a short time in order to become a housewife, but she disliked the role. She soon re-enrolled in philosophy and art classes at the University of Houston. In 1957, she became an account executive for an ad agency, and was invited to teach classes in journalism and literature at a four-year woman's university in Houston called Dominican College.
In 1959, Helen Barthelme started her own ad agency, and continued to teach at Dominican College. She and Donald Barthelme were divorced in 1965. She continued her education, getting her doctorate from the University of Texas at Austin. In 1972, she accepted an appointment with the Department of English at the University of Houston. She went on to become a professor of English at Texas A&M university in College Station. Helen Barthelme had a long and distinguished career as an ad executive and professor. She died of cancer on Jun 28, 2002.
Sources:
Barthelme, H. M. (2001). Donald Barthelme: The Genesis of a Cool Sound (Tarleton State University Southwestern Studies in the Humanities, 13) (1st ed ed.). College Station: Texas A&M University Press.
Contemporary Authors Online, Gale, 2010. Reproduced in Biography Resource Center. Farmington Hills, Mich.: Gale, 2010. http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/BioRC
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston -- Alumni and alumnae; University of Houston -- Faculty
Genre/Form of Material:
Articles; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Photographs
Personal Name:
Barthelme, Donald; Barthelme, Helen Moore, 1927-
Title:
Forum (Houston, Tex.)
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains photographs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, short stories, and articles related to or written by Donald Barthelme and his brothers, Rick, Steve, and Peter Barthelme, as well as notes by Helen Barthelme. This collection contains research that Helen Barthelme gathered in order to write a biography on Donald Barthelme Jr., Donald Barthelme: The Genesis of a Cool Sound. This collection encompasses his early life and career both as a writer and as director of the Contemporary Arts Association, up until his death in 1989.
Detailed List of Contents
- Early Life and Career, 1949-1989, undated
  - High school graduation program, award, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles published, copies, 1949-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harvest, 1952-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Then" story, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscelleneous architectural speech, Rice University lectures, etc. (Donald Barthelme Sr.), 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Natanson class notes, Spring 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Class notes, Spring 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Natanson lecture notes, 1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lecture notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Requisitions to University of Houston, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscelleneous bills, statements, etc., 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cards, documents, 1952-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ACPRA meeting, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Arts Career, 1960-1978, undated
    This series includes copies of typescript program proposals for the Contemporary Arts Association (CAA) and the Contemporary Arts Museum, CAA publications, copies of newspaper articles about CAA, and other miscellaneous materials.
    - CAA, other materials, 1960-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - CAA clippings, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Contains microfiche copies of newspaper articles about CAA during Donald Barthelme's tenureas member of the board and director.
    - CAA newspaper articles, 1961-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1989
    This series includes original, and copies of typescript letters written by Donald Barthelme to his family during his army service in Korea, to Helen Barthelme during and after their marriage, and to friends and family. The series also includes letters to Donald Barthelme from friends, postcards, telegrams, and other miscellaneous items. Some letters included are outside the chronological scope of the early years of Donald Barthelme's life.
    - Korea, 1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters to parents, NY, Europe, 1962-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letters to Helen Barthelme, 1963-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Miscelleneous correspondence, friends, 1950-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Gollub, Henry, 1958-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Maranto, Joe, 1953-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, 1950-1960
    This series contains photographs from Donald Barthelme's time in Korea, his selective service cards and honorable discharge certificate from the US Army, and family photographs, slides, negatives, and proofs.
    - Family, 1950's-1960's, undated
      - Barthelme brothers, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Barthelme family, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Beach photos with Jack and Ann Boynton, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Donald Barthelme, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Donald Barthelme and Helen Barthelme, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Donald Barthelme, Anne, and Birgit, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Helen Barthelme, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Houston Chronicle photo, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Miscellaneous family photos, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Negatives, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Proofs, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Slides, Christmas, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Korea, 1953-1961
      - Base camp, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Christmas, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - City pictures, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Honorable Discharge, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Individual, enlisted men, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Landscapes, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Military vehicles, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - People of Korea, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Proofs, base and enlisted men, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Proofs, people & city, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Selective service registration cards, 1949, 1955, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Theater, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Training soldiers, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Unknown ship, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Volleyball game, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - Weapons training, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Winter, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Forum Magazine Editorial Career, 1956-1993, undated
  - Forum Correspondence, 1956-1993
    This series includes correspondence between Donald Barthelme and contributors to the Forum during 1956-1960, arranged alphabetically by contributor name. Included are letters from such noted contributors as Robert Bly, Irving Howe, Alfred Kazin, Norman Mailer, and Harold Rosenberg. Some folders also include additional materials related to Forum contributors such as reprints of articles, photocopied bibliographies of works, photocopies of obituaries, and annotated lists of correspondence. Also included is correspondence related to a propsed meeting of editors of similar journals and miscellaneous administrative materials.
    - Annotated list of letters to Donald Barthelme, 1956-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Aldridge, John, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Barth, John, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Blackmur, R.P., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bly, Robert, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Borklund, Elmer W., 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Brooks, Bruce, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Collins, James, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Corrigan, Robert W., 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Corrington, William, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Coser, Lewis A., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Cowley, Malcolm, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Dienstfrey, Harris, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Dugger, Ronnie, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ellenberger, Henri F., 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Fiedler, Leslie A., 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Gass, William H., 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Gerhard, William A., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Hayakawa, S.I., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Howe, Irving, 1957-1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Jones, Jack, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Karlen, Arno, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Kazan, Elia, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Kazin, Alfred, 1958-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Kenner, Hugh, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Kubrick, Stanley, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Lyons, Joseph, 1958-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - MacAgy, Douglas, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Mailer, Norman, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - McLuhan, Marshall, 1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Meyerhoff, Hans, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Mudrick, Marvin, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Mumford, Lewis, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Moynahan, Julian, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Natanson, Maurice, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Nemerov, Howard, 1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Peterson, Robert, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Podhoretz, Norman, 1958-1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Riesman, David, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Rosenberg, Harold, 1959-1978 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Schorer, Mark, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Stafford, William, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Straus, Edwin W., 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Tyler, Parker, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Walker, Stanley, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - White, E.B., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Yates, Peter, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Forum, 1956-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence from Donald Barthelme, 1957-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence Copies, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - University of Houston Forum proposed meeting of editors: Correspondence from Donald Barthelme and editors, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence with publishers Re stories, articles, payments for services, other correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - University of Houston correspondence: Nicholson, etc. Report on FORUM resignation, editorial board, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Forum Magazine and Miscellaneous Manuscript Materials, 1954-1960, undated
    This series includes original and copies of Forum magazines and other miscellaneous materials.
    - University of Houston Forum miscelleneous manuscript materials, 1954-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Forum, September, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Forum, January 1957 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Forum, April 1957 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Forum, Summer 1957 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Forum, Fall 1957 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Forum, May 1958 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Forum, Fall 1958 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Forum, Spring 1959 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Forum, Summer 1959 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Forum, Fall 1959 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Forum, Summer 1960 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Forum, Fall, Winter 1965 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Reprints of Forum articles, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Writing, 1961-1990
  This series contains several photocopies and originals of the published versions of early short stories by Donald Barthelme, an original typescript of his essay "Not-Knowing," and miscellaneous materials related to Barthelme's writing work. It also includes a listing of the published versions of short stories, which were cataloged and removed from the collection.
  - "The Darling Duckling at School," Contact, photocopy, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "The Hiding Man," First Person, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Three", photocopy, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Not Knowing," typescript and copy, Georgia Review original lecture article., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The Good People at Sam's Bar", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "The King", uncorrected proof title page, photocopy, description, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - New York Writer's Conference, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Agents, 1966-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Short stories records list, 1967-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Reviews/Biographical Articles, 1964-2000, undated
  This series contains copies of newspaper and magazine articles about Barthelme and his work, interviews, reviews of works, and miscellaneous critical materials. Also included are programs for book readings of Barthelme's works and receptions honoring Barthelme, as well as the announcement of the Barthelme Memorial Fellowship award.
  - Miscelleneous, event programs and announcements, 1973-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscelleneous critical materials, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reviews/biographical articles, clippings from magazines, 1964-1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Interviews, 1973-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Biographies (essay on Don), Phillip Lopate, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscelleneous notes (reviewer), 2000, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews: obituaries, July 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, copies of newspaper and magazine articles, and reviews, 1990-1997 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Fredrick, Peter, and Steven Barthelme, 1967-1998
  This series includes copies of newspaper articles on the Barthelme brothers, reviews of their works, and essays published by Steven Barthelme. The series also contains copies of 'The Texas Observer' during Steven Barthelme's tenure as review editor and contributor.
  - Fredrick Barthelme, 1967-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Peter Barthelme, 1973-1996 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Steve Barthelme, includes the typescript of the essay "Proust at Lunch", 1988-1992, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Steven Barthelme, copies of "The Texas Observer", 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Steve and Rick Barthelme, article on violation of gambling laws, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Helen Barthelme, 1956-2001, undated
  - Book Research for Donald Barthelme: The Genesis of a Cool Sound, 1956-2001, undated
    This series includes notes for Helen Barthelme's book, analysis of Donald Barthelme's works, interviews with friends of Donald Barthelme, biographies and bibliographies of contributors to Forum, newspaper and magazine articles about Donald Barthelme, and other miscellaneous materials.
    - Army, Korean War notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Copies of family letters, with chapters noted, 1962-1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Biographical, 1952-1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Reviews, stories, miscelleneous, 1967-1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Pete Barthelme interview, miscellaneous, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Interviews, Geo., Mary Christian, Joe Maranto, Pat Goeters, 1990-1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Pat Goeters, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Henry Gollob, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Joe Maranto, 1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Walker Percy, 1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - New York Times Book Reviews, microfiche copies, 1956-1962 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - List of Works by Authors of Letters, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Biographies, miscelleneous, 1989-1998, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Notes for Book, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Review of "Donald Barthelme: The Genesis of a Cool Sound", 2001 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - University of Houston Materials Research/Reference, 1957-1959, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Personal writing, 1968-1997
    This series includes manuscripts, notes, and diaries by Helen Barthelme, drafts of fictional works, poems, and essays, including Dr. Barthelme's classwork.
    - Diary Notes, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Diary notes, Donald Barthelme death, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Jewel Beulah Moore manuscript notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Helen Barthelme Beeville, other manuscript miscellaneous notes, etc., 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Manuscripts, 1968-1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Snow White", 1967-1990 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "Snow White," notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "Margins", undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Ricoeur, Paul, 1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Notes: other reference materials Sam Southwell, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Sam Southwell, Warrior, other notes, lectures, 1983-1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Helen Barthelme, 1962-2002 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Proofs, Helen Barthelme, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)